Finding aid to the Women and Life on Earth records SSC.MS.00132
Sophia Smith Collection
Women and Life on Earth records
1979-2009
1980-82
Sophia Smith Collection
Women and Life on Earth
SSC.MS.00132
12 boxes (11.25 linear feet)
The collection contains the papers of Women and Life on Earth, on peace, anti-nuclear, and ecofeminist network. Records include conference materials, correspondence, minutes by-laws, financial records, newsletters, writings, talks, clippings, subject files, notes, posters, photographs, memorabilia, and audio tapes.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use with following restrictions on access: Collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be somewhat difficult to use. Original AV and born-digital materials may not be used; research use copies must be made. Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice. Researchers must sign Access Agreement form agreeing to not identify living persons without their permission.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was gifted by Anna Gyorgy in 2003, 2005, and 2009.
Biographical / Historical
Women and Life on Earth (WLOE) was founded in August 1979, after the accident at the Three Mile Island nuclear plant in Pennsylvania by 12 women from the northeastern U.S. who were active in anti-nuclear, alternative energy, peace and women's organizations. They were concerned about the "proliferation of nuclear weapons and technologies, toxic wastes, urban decay, and ecologically destructive means of production," and the threats posed to the quality of life on earth. They formed WLOE to "bring these concerns into the political arena." The organization's kick-off event was a conference: "Women and Life on Earth: A Conference on Eco-Feminism in the '80s," held in March, 1980 (the spring equinox) at the University of Massachusetts, Amherst. It brought together 600 women from the northeastern U.S. WLOE took advantage of the momentum generated by the conference and organized the Women's Pentagon Action, an anti-nuclear protest. In November 1980, 2,000 women encircled the Pentagon in Arlington, Virginia, demanding "no more amazing inventions for death." Women and Life on Earth activities continued in the U.S. and Britain for several years. The original WLOE network's activities ended in 1982.
In 1999 WLOE launched the Women and Life on Earth Internet project "to connect women internationally, share information and support changes necessary to ensure life and peace with justice in the new millennium." In August 1999 an international board of advisors was formed at a meeting held in western Massachusetts. In 2001 the project moved to Berlin, Germany with coordinator Anna Gyorgy, and the 'war on terror' that followed the September 11, 2001 attacks in the U.S., and the wars in Afghanistan and Iraq "gave further proof of the need for international communication and solidarity for peace with justice."
In January 2004 the German-based association (full name: "Women and Life on Earth: women for international cooperation for peace, ecology and social justice") was granted non-profit status. They currently have an active email mailing list and Web site, and publish an electronic newsletter in German and English, to report on "women and peace, globalization and ecology." It also organizes local programs and guest speakers. [Source: WLOE Web site: http://www.wloe.org]
Scope and Contents
Records include only to the original WLOE activities which ended in 1982 and include planning materials pertaining to "Women and Life on Earth: A Conference on Eco-Feminism in the '80s," held at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst (March 1980); and the Women's Pentagon Action (Washington, DC, Nov. 1980), both organized by WLOE. Additional materials include correspondence, minutes by-laws, financial records, newsletters, writings, talks, clippings, subject files related to the environment and peace, notes, posters, photographs, memorabilia, and audio tapes.
Antinuclear movement--History--Sources; Ecofeminism--History--Sources; Environmental protection--Citizen participation--History--Sources; Nuclear disarmament--History--Sources; Nuclear power plants--Environmental aspects; Pacifists--History--20th century--Sources; Peace--Societies, etc.--History--Sources; Peace movements--History--20th century--Sources; Women environmentalists--History--Sources; Women and peace--History--20th century--Sources; Women--International cooperation--History--20th century--Sources; Women's Pentagon Action (1980: Arlington, Va.); Audiotapes; Brochures; Bylaws; clippings; correspondence; Electronic mail; Financial records; Fliers; Forms (documents); Fund raising; Invoices; Mailing lists; Membership lists; Memorandums; Newsletters; Minutes; Newspapers; notebooks; Notes; Pamphlets; press releases; Questionnaires; Computer media; Gyorgy, Anna; Women and Life on Earth--History--Sources; Women and Life on Earth: A Conference on Eco-Feminism in the '80s," (1980: Amherst, Mass.); Women and Life on Earth; Gyorgy, Anna; Women and Life on Earth
- WLOE conferences on eco-feminism and Women's Pentagon Action, 1979-2003; 2003-S-0017; Gyorgy, Anna; 7 linear feet (7 boxes. Other materials: posters in flat file)
  Gyorgy, Anna
  - Materials related to "Women and Life on Earth: A Conference on Eco-Feminism in the '80s," held at University of Massachusetts, Amherst, March, 1980-1983 (Box 1)
  - Transcriptions of speeches given at conference, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Newsletter copy, No date (Box 5)
  - Posters, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
  - Photographs, No date (Box 6)
  - Booklet: "As a Woman Thinketh", No date (Box 6)
  - Women's Pentagon Action fliers and brochures, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Women's Pentagon Action correspondence, 1981 (Box 6)
  - Women's Pentagon Action evaluations, 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - Women's Pentagon Action notes and memoranda about t-shirts, 1981 (Box 6)
  - Women's Pentagon Action unity statement, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Women's Pentagon Action raffle: fliers, memoranda and raffle tickets, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Women's Pentagon Action bus lists, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Women's Pentagon Action racism workshop transcription, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Women's Pentagon Action clippings, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Women's Pentagon Action poster, 1980 (Box 6)
  - WLOE logo designs, No date (Box 6)
  - WLOE regional planning meeting: agendas, brochures and fliers, 1999 (Box 6)
  - WLOE newsletter, Tidings, 1980-05 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, No date (Box 6)
  - Button, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Electronic newsletters, 1999; 1999, 2002-2003 (Box 6)
  - Audiotapes, 1980, No date (Box 7)
    - Forty-three unlabeled tapes regarding "Women and Life on Earth: A Conference on Eco-Feminism in the '80s", 1980 (Box 7)
    - "WISE," (9 tapes), 1980 (Box 7)
    - "Women and Nukes," (2 tapes), No date (Box 7)
    - "Feminism and ecology," (1 tape), No date (Box 7)
    - "Milagros workshop," (1 tape), No date (Box 7)
    - "Helen Moreschi: Women in Trade Unions," (1 tape), No date (Box 7)
    - "Kayla Bicker: Genetic Manipulation," (1 tape), No date
    - "Confronting Racism," (1 tape), No date (Box 7)
    - "Urban community organizing," (2 tapes), No date (Box 7)
    - "Women and Wilderness," (1 tape), No date (Box 7)
- WLOE 1980 conference and Pentagon Action materials, 1980-1981; 2005-S-0059; 2 linear feet
  - Women's Pentagon Action clippings, 1980-1981; 2005-S-0059 (Box 1)
  - Women's Pentagon Action fliers, memoranda, and press releases, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Women's Pentagon Action photographs (contact sheets), 1980 (Box 1)
  - Address cards including WLOE conference, Amherst, MA, 1980 and no date (Box 1)
  - Undelivered mail, including WLOE conference in Amherst, MA, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Original artwork and clippings from Women's Pentagon Action, 1980; 2005-S-0059 (Box 2)
  - Audiotapes from WLOE conference in Amherst, MA, 1980; 2005-S-0059 (Box 3)
- WLOE 1980 conference audio CDs, 2008-2009; 2009-S-0020a; Gyorgy, Anna; 0.5 linear feet
  - Preservation masters of CDs, 1980 WLOE Conference, Amherst, 1980-1986; Accession 2009-S-0020a (Box 1)
  - Research use CD copies, 1980 WLOE conference, Amherst, Accession 2009-S-0020a (Box 2)
  - Audio CD, "Women, Militarism and the Arms Race.", No date; Accession 2009-S-0020a (Box 2)
  - Audio CD, "Is There a Feminine Perspective?", No date; Accession 2009-S-0020a (Box 2)
  - Audio CD, "Communicating Environmental and Feminist Issues, No date; Accession 2009-S-0020a (Box 2)
  - Audio CD, "Women and the Anti-nuke Movement/Eco-feminist Organizing", No date; Accession 2009-S-0020 (Box 2)